<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-14T23:47:35-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project Charter and Other Good Stuff]]></title>
    <link href="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/charter/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-13T19:43:05-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/charter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>A Brief Overview</h3>

<p>Otto is your personalized, robot bartender. Simply send a drink order to Otto from your phone, tablet, or computer and the drink will be prepared otto-matically to your tastes.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Our Approach – Otto</h3>

<p>Otto has three key components: the liquor, the mixers, and the glass. The liquor will be gravity fed and regulated via solenoids hooked up to the Arduino. The mixers are a little trickier since by and large they need to be refrigerated. To address this, we&rsquo;ll keep the mixers in a minifridge beneath the main unit (where they are also regulated by solenoids) and pumped upwards by a powerful peristaltic pump. The glass will ideally remain stationary and be fed by the appropriate tubes.</p>

<p>On the software side of things, the Arduino will be hooked up to a Raspberry Pi functioning as a server running node.js. Here we&rsquo;ll host a website that allows users to order their drinks and interface with Otto easily and conveniently.</p>

<p>The team members are Rustin Manafian, Chris Weller, and Ryne Chaloux. Everyone on the team is equally experienced in the skills required for this project, so the roles are fluid and adaptable. Individual ownership of various parts of the project can be determined as the need for it arises, but this project will be managed as a pseudo-flat organization.</p>

<h3>Objectives, Milestones and the &ldquo;What&rdquo; of Otto</h3>

<p>Ideally by the end of our 10 week sprint, we&rsquo;d like to have a deliverable, bar tending robot capable of making basic cocktails and getting you drunk for $500 or less. A rough outline of what this might entail on the production side of things would be to start by opening and closing the valves, get excited once we&rsquo;ve figured out how to rig up all the mixers, and offer up a toast once our first shot&rsquo;s been poured.</p>

<p>Any potential long term goals would be centered around getting the user liquored up faster, cheaper, and in a more stylish way.</p>

<p>The primary deliverable would be&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>06/06/14</strong> Otto, the project we&rsquo;ve been rambling on about.</p>

<p>We will all be held equally responsible for this.</p>

<h3>Constraints, Risk and Feasibility, and Other Excuses</h3>

<p>Seeing as none of us have taken on a hardware project of this stature, simply learning all the necessary components of circuit design and implementation is one such risk taken with this project. However, after a cursory search when we came up with the project (and now further in, having been entrenched in hardware design for the past 3 weeks), we have determined that while ambitious, this project is feasible.</p>

<p>Other potential stumbling blocks include lack of viable suppliers or back ordered supplies, tight budgets, design issues such as where and how to mount what, and various things of that nature. Thankfully we&rsquo;ve already mitigated most of these concerns. We&rsquo;ve set a soft budge we&rsquo;ve all agreed upon of roughly $500, we&rsquo;ve bought and sourced parts from local suppliers, and we&rsquo;re actively consulting people with light years more experience than us in the food safe hardware field.</p>

<h2>Group Management</h2>

<p><strong>What are the major roles in your group’s management?</strong></p>

<p>There are no management roles. Everybody is as much in charge as everybody else. We strive to be a flatly organized team.</p>

<p><strong>How will decisions be made? By leader, consensus?</strong></p>

<p>Decisions will be made by consensus. An odd number ensures tie breaking, and if anyone&rsquo;s on the fence, <a href="http://random.org">Random.org</a> is here to save the day.</p>

<p><strong>How will you communicate? Email, meetings in the lab, discussion board?</strong></p>

<p>We will communicate through Google Hangouts and texting on top of meeting in person once or more a week as needed. We&rsquo;re all guaranteed to be on campus at various times throughout the week, and we&rsquo;ve set up a Google Calendar that reflects this.</p>

<p><strong>How will you know when you’re off schedule, and how will you deal with schedule slips?</strong></p>

<p>Seeings as our milestones are laid out already, it&rsquo;s fairly negligible for us to check against them in our weekly meetings. If we aren&rsquo;t actively making progress on any one milestone from week to week, we&rsquo;ll know we&rsquo;ve got a problem. Should we have schedule slips, we&rsquo;ll deal with them on a case by case basis.</p>

<p>But realistically, if Otto isn&rsquo;t working as we&rsquo;d hoped by when we&rsquo;d hoped, we&rsquo;ll just retroactively edit our schedule so that we can be back on schedule.</p>

<p><strong>Who is responsible for which deliverables and milestones?</strong></p>

<p>Everybody is equally responsible. Everyone in the group is expected to volunteer to work towards finishing the project.</p>

<p><strong>Who will produce the weekly group status reports?</strong>
Probably Rustin. He has the best handwriting.</p>

<h2>Project Development</h2>

<p><strong>What are the development roles and who will handle them?</strong>
There are no specific roles. Everyone on the team will volunteer to do whatever needs to get done.</p>

<p><strong>What hardware/software will you use? What do you have available? What do you need?</strong></p>

<p>We need an Arduino, Raspberry Pi, various solenoid valves, peristaltic pump, resistors, transistors, diodes, LEDs, a power supply, a mini fridge, connecting tubing and hardware, and probably some more stuff that we&rsquo;ll figure out later. This is all subject to change.</p>

<p><strong>If there is software/hardware that is needed, provide a justification for its cost. Where will you order it? When will it arrive?</strong></p>

<p>This hardware is necessary because without it we can&rsquo;t build Otto. We&rsquo;ve already ordered and received most of it. A lot of stuff is available in San Diego. All of it is available from America to shorten shipping times and reduce lead content.</p>

<p><strong>How will you do testing?</strong></p>

<p>By getting very drunk.</p>

<p><strong>How will you do documentation?</strong></p>

<p>By getting very drunk.</p>

<h2>Project Schedule</h2>

<p><strong>1</strong> &nbsp;Open/close solenoid (Completed! &ndash; April 11th)<br>
<strong>2</strong> &nbsp;Connect solenoid to bottle (Expected &ndash; April 19)<br>
<strong>3</strong> &nbsp;Consistently dispense one ounce (Expected &ndash; April 20)<br>
<strong>4</strong> &nbsp;Rig up all 6 liquor solenoids (Expected &ndash; April 25)<br>
<strong>5</strong> &nbsp;Dispense from multiple sources into glass (Expected &ndash; April 26)<br>
<strong>6</strong> &nbsp;LEDs up in this bitch (Expected &ndash; April 26)<br>
<strong>7</strong> &nbsp;Run peristaltic pump with just one mixer (Expected &ndash; May 1)<br>
<strong>8</strong> &nbsp;Extend pump setup with 6 mixers and their respective solenoids (Expected &ndash; May 3)<br>
<strong>9</strong> &nbsp;More LEDs (Expected &ndash; May 3)<br>
<strong>10</strong> Mount everything (Expected &ndash; May 21)<br>
<strong>11</strong> Make an AMF (our benchmark drink) (Expected &ndash; May 30)<br>
<strong>12</strong> Make it pretty (optional) (Expected &ndash; June 4)<br></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Story So Far]]></title>
    <link href="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/the-story-so-far/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-13T11:58:43-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/the-story-so-far</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We started out having no idea how we could make OTTO a reality. Well, to go back a bit further, we started out having no idea what project we were actually competent enough to complete. An acoustic keyboard sniffer? Too much math. A differential power analysis attack? Too much what the fuck is this. An automated pancake flipper? Too many carbs. OTTO came to fruition because it was the perfect mix of engaging to work on, exciting to demo, and a good excuse to get trashed before 5. <!--more--></p>

<p>Now that we had the idea we began the hard work of making it happen. The project has two basic components: get the glass to move and find a way to dispense the liquid. As it turns out, dispensing the liquid is pretty goddamn tricky. You can pump the liquid upwards. There are definitely solutions available but they’re either expensive, ugly, slow, or some combination thereof. We saw an existing project that used breast pumps. As tempting as it is, we didn’t see ourselves marching down to Breast-Pumps-R-Us and buying 6 breast pumps. Another project used peristaltic pumps each individually controlled by an arduino connected to a raspberry pi over ethernet. That seemed way too complicated to us. Really, why not let gravity do the work? This is in fact such a good idea that another bar robot uses it. However, the makers of said robot refuse to release any schematics, part list, source code, or anything that might interfere with this idea that they seem to have that they will become billionaires from bar machines. So we had to do it ourselves.</p>

<p>The first gravity solution that we looked into was a servo that would turn a valve. After spending half an hour in Home Depot turning valves and attempting to assess the amount of torque required we learned a few things. One, there is a surprising variety of valves out there. Two, the sheer amount of torque required would necessitate an impractically expensive servo. Three, none of us fit in at a hardware store.</p>

<p>We pressed on in searching for valves for our project. Eventually, we came upon the aptly titled valves4projects. We found food safe solenoids for $14/piece <a href="http://www.ebay.com/itm/1-2-Gravity-Feed-Electric-Solenoid-Valve-DDB-CD-12VDC-/300653378588?pt=LH_DefaultDomain_0&amp;hash=item4600567c1c">here</a>! These were perfect for our project so we ordered 6. Conveniently enough, valves4projects is located in downtown San Diego. So after heading downtown for a quick pick-up, we went over to San Diego Electronic Supply where Manny the manager hooked it fat. For starters, this store is amazing as long as you can manage not to trip on the pile of boxes that greet you in the entrance, to the right of the entrance, to the right of the right of the entrance, to the left of the right of the right of the entrance, and really just the whole store. We walked in knowing basically nothing about transistors, resistors, diodes, and circuits, but, as I said before, Manny hooked it up. After giving us a brief 101 on circuits, he did some sort of wizard math and scooped up all the parts for us. We walked out of there with:</p>

<ul>
<li>6 1N4004 diodes</li>
<li>6 3.3k resistors</li>
<li>6 TIP111 transistors</li>
<li>12V 5.5A power supply</li>
</ul>


<p>for the princely sum of $14.</p>

<p>Now, the exciting part begins. We returned with our spoils and started plugging away at breadboarding it. We managed to get the solenoid opening and closing that same night. Considering that we were expecting that part to take a week or two, we were pleasantly surprised. Encouraged by this success, we began plotting our next improvement to OTTO: refrigerated mixers! Once we actually figure out how to do this, we’ll share it with you guys. Stay tuned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
