<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Otto, The Truly Open Mixer]]></title>
  <link href="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-10T22:20:52-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Team OTTO]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TEST PLS IGNORE]]></title>
    <link href="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/06/02/TEST-PLS-IGNORE/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T22:49:51-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/06/02/TEST-PLS-IGNORE</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/images/1.jpg" style="width: 100%" />
<img src="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/images/2.jpg" style="width: 100%" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Story So Far Part 2: Final Milestone Update]]></title>
    <link href="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/05/19/the-story-so-far-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-19T22:49:51-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/05/19/the-story-so-far-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the purposes of this report, we’ll be referring to our revised list of milestones. Throughout the quarter, our list of milestones has grown longer and longer to the point that the original list of milestones is comical. Additionally, some of our original milestones weren’t thought through very well. For example, some are in fact dependent on the whole project being done so they are redundant as milestones. For another example, consider the milestone we had of hooking up 6 solenoids. That milestone has building a mount as a prerequisite so it doesn’t make sense for that to be first. In short, we ended up changing a lot of dates to be more sane. And finally some of our milestones simply ended up being absorbed by others. So, without further ado here’s our current milestones:</p>

<!--more-->


<p><strong>Completed (Pictures/Video follows each set of milestones)</strong></p>

<p>Open/close solenoid (Completed! – April 11th)</p>

<p>Connect solenoid to bottle (Expected – April 19) (Completed! – April 20th)</p>

<p>Consistently dispense one ounce (Expected – April 20) (Completed! – April 20th)</p>

<div class='embed-container'>
<iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/liqCEJRP9Pk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>Run peristaltic pump with just one mixer (Expected – May 1) (Completed! – May 3)</p>

<p><em>This picture actually has two</em>
<img src="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/images/old_mount_2_cup_pump.jpg" style="width: 100%" /></p>

<p>Set up the BeagleBone (Completed! – May 3)</p>

<p>Use Johnny-five to control the solenoids/pump from the BeagleBone (Completed! – May 3)</p>

<p>Create a settings page for OTTO (Completed! – April 23)
<img src="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/images/settings.png" style="width: 100%" />
Create a menu page for OTTO (Completed! – April 27)
<img src="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/images/menu.png" style="width: 100%" />
Create an “Add a Recipe” page for OTTO (Completed! – May 12)
<img src="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/images/recipes.png" style="width: 100%" /></p>

<p><strong>Almost Complete (with commentary)</strong></p>

<p>Rig up all 6 liquor solenoids (Expected – May 21)</p>

<p><em>We’ve made good progress on assembling the caps and just need to add a bit of glue to make them permanent. Then, we’ll just need to cut some wire and hook it all up to the power supply.</em>
<img src="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/images/cap.jpg" style="width: 100%" /></p>

<p>Extend pump with 6 mixers and solenoids (Expected – May 31)</p>

<p><em>We’ve hooked up 4 of the mixer solenoids to the pump and the power supply. The only thing left is to repeat what we’ve done for the remaining 2.</em>
<img src="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/images/solenoids_in_fridge.jpg" style="width: 100%" /></p>

<p>Mount everything (Expected – May 21)</p>

<p><em>We’ve devised a mount that works although it does look a bit ugly. We’re working on developing something nicer. If we have to we’ll use the less visually appealing bottle mount.</em>
<img src="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/images/old_mount_final.jpg" style="width: 100%" /></p>

<div class='embed-container'>
<iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/Z0_legeFDXw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p><img src="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/images/new_mount.jpg" style="width: 100%" />
<img src="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/images/wood_enclosure.jpg" style="width: 100%" />
Solder everything (Expected – May 24)</p>

<p><em>We’ve started running all the wires, but we’ve just tied them in. Once we decide exactly what we want we’ll solder and use heat shrink wrap to make it all permanent.</em>
<img src="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/images/solenoid_circuit.jpg" style="width: 100%" /></p>

<p><strong>No Work Done</strong></p>

<p>Implement a queue for OTTO (Expected – June 1)</p>

<p>Add a weight sensor to detect a glass (Expected – Whenever (if) we have time)</p>

<p>Even though we’re still on track to finish, it looks like we won’t have time to implement some of our stretch goals. We have been spending a lot of time just running around San Diego trying to get together all the parts we need. We almost had a major setback on Saturday when we were working with the mini-fridge. We kind of broke the freon line so all the gas escaped and the fridge is basically broken. We managed to find someone on Craigslist that very same day that was selling a bigger, better fridge. It was a detour of several hours that could have easily morphed into a serious setback. That aside, we&rsquo;ve been doing really well making steady progress everyday.</p>

<p><strong>Sprint</strong></p>

<!-- I know this is disgusting. mama please forgive me. -->


<p>Team<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;Week 8<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Decide on and finalize enclosure<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;Week 9<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Solder everything<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Mount everything within our determined enclosure<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;Week 10<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Testing<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Testing<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Testing<br /></p>

<p>Chris<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;Week 8<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Compile Redis on BeagleBone Black<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Configure to run when web instance is deployed<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;Week 9<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Implement Kue for drinks queue<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Mount everything within our determined enclosure<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;Week 10<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Test stability with concurrent MongoDB/Redis Cache<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Investigate speeding up website with web caching<br /></p>

<p>Rustin<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;Week 8<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Responsive layout fixes<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Add additional unit options (e.g. ml, dashses)<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;Week 9<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Theming<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Testing and bugfixes<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;Week 10<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Testing and bugfixes<br /></p>

<p>Ryne<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;Week 8<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Spearhead effort on newer, better enclosure<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;Week 9<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Implement live menu filtration based on installed drinks<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Determine optimal drinks for pre-installation and demo<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;Week 10<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Populate database with valuable recipes based on demo drinks<br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It Pours! Part 2 (What We've Been Up To)]]></title>
    <link href="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/04/27/it-pours-part-2-what-weve-been-up-to/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-27T22:24:50-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/04/27/it-pours-part-2-what-weve-been-up-to</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This update will be brief, but exciting. We&rsquo;ve recently shifted our focus to the software side of OTTO. We&rsquo;re running a <a href="http://mean.io">MEAN stack</a> server with <a href="https://github.com/rwaldron/johnny-five">Johnny-five</a> controlling the Arduino. To make a long story short, OTTO is now at the point where we can press a button on the website to fire off the solenoids and the pump.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Now, the really exciting part about all of this is that two weeks ago none of us knew anything about MEAN stack. Hell, I don&rsquo;t even think that we knew what those initials stand for (Mongo, Express, Angular, and Node in case you were wondering). We divided the project into frontend, backend, and database and had each person learn a part. Then, we shared what we learned amongst each other. This did the trick and now we have a working website. We still have a ways to go until it&rsquo;s totally polished, but we&rsquo;ve got a solid foundation.</p>

<p>Finally, we&rsquo;ve had some minor setbacks. As it turns out, the Raspberry Pi is not fast enough to run our server and communicate with the Arduino with the precise timing we need. After some searching we found the <a href="http://beagleboard.org/Products/BeagleBone+Black">BeagleBone Black</a> which gave us a collective, massive BeagleBoner. The BBB is faster, has more GPIO slots than we know what to do with, and has recently been made compatible with johnny-five. Unfortunately that shit is so dial toned that we could not order it from a single goddamn place no matter how hard we looked. For now, we&rsquo;re just running the server from our laptops. This certainly works, but we hope to acquire a BBB to reduce the overall project size. We implore you to stay tuned as we&rsquo;ll be having a build weekend soon!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[To Be Stuck Inside of San Diego With the Can't Find the Goddamn Parts I Need Blues Again]]></title>
    <link href="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/04/25/to-be-stuck-inside-of-san-diego-with-the-cant-find-the-goddamn-parts-i-need-blues-again/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-25T14:41:55-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/04/25/to-be-stuck-inside-of-san-diego-with-the-cant-find-the-goddamn-parts-i-need-blues-again</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>All I needed was a few tee fittings and some rubber stoppers. Conviently for me, there was a plumbing supply warehouse across from a bar supply warehouse. This should be easy, right?</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I called the plumbing supply guys to make sure they had the &frac12;&#8221; and &frac14;&#8221; barbed food safe tee fittings that I needed. They did. Perfect. Except when I got there, it turned out that the guy looked up the wrong parts and they had exactly 0 of the ones I wanted in their warehouse. The helfpul saleslady directed me to a hardware store literally across the street. I thanked her and drove over (of course, because I live in Southern California).</p>

<p>This hardware store, Marshall&rsquo;s Industrial Hardware, was simply awesome. I&rsquo;m not planning on going back to Home Despot any time soon. I followed the advice of a large sign that said &ldquo;IF YOU CAN&rsquo;T FIND SOMETHING PLEASE ASK&rdquo; and after being handed off once or twice, came to an aisle with some tee fittings. So far so good. Then I ask the guy if the fittings are food safe. He just says they&rsquo;re made out of nylon, which doesn&rsquo;t really help.</p>

<p>So, I called the guys listed as the source for the fittings. After waiting on hold for a bit, I found out that they are only distributors and had no idea whether or not the fittings were food safe. The lady on the phone tried her damnedest to find out, but handed me to off the manufacturer when she couldn&rsquo;t. Equipped with the manufacturer&rsquo;s phone number and the model number of the part, I found light at the end of the tunnel. The guy that answered knew right away. In fact, someone had just asked him if these fittings were food safe. You might think that if this question comes up so frequently, that they would make it more visible, but I digress.</p>

<p>On to the stoppers. We specifically needed Rabbit Stoppers, for reasons detailed in the previous post. The bar supply place down the street didn&rsquo;t have them so I went to BevMo where they only came in two packs. We wanted to color code each slot with a different colored bottle stopper. The problem with the two-packs is that we would have duplicates. So, I called up Crate &amp; Barrel and found that they had plenty of single stoppers in stock. Great! Except I showed up and realized that they only had one color. When things don&rsquo;t go according to plan, you change your plans. I decided that having different colors was stupid, we never wanted to do that, and that a single color was really the best idea.</p>

<p>Now, the good news! After running around all day we are incredibly close to having all the parts. We&rsquo;ve spent $300 so far, can we stay under our $500 budget? Pretty please with a cherry on top, stay tuned to find out!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Good News Everyone! It Pours!]]></title>
    <link href="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/04/20/good-news-everyone-it-pours/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-20T20:15:19-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/04/20/good-news-everyone-it-pours</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The title says it all. Check out the video below and then we&rsquo;ll walk you through the technical stuff afterwards.</p>

<div class='embed-container'>
<iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/liqCEJRP9Pk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<!--more-->


<p>As you may have been able to ascertain, we were a little excited about pouring that first shot. That was our first take and we honestly didn&rsquo;t expect it to work. We had our fair share of hurdles and were totally blown away by the outcome.</p>

<p>The rough idea for the design had always been to connect a solenoid to an upside down bottle then keep it open for a certain time per ounce (as bartenders do when they pour a shot). That is much easier said than done.</p>

<p>The most obvious solution was to take shot pourer and use a union and some tubing to join it to the solenoid. The most obvious solution is usually wrong, however,  and this was no exception. The reason that bartenders can reliably count to pour a shot is because they get a consistent flow from the shot pourer. The shot pourer gets a consistent flow because it has a breather tube that allows air back into the bottle as the liquid is dispensed. The problem is that if you turn the bottle upside down and close off the spout of the pourer, your (presumably) expensive liquor will slowly leak out. That&rsquo;s simply not acceptable.</p>

<p>The crux of the matter is that we would need a breather tube that could let air in, but not let alcohol out. We tested this by hot gluing a bendy straw on top of the breather hole of our pourer. It worked! Pretty much. Fast forward a bit and we found a rubber bottle stopper that we could adapt to our purposes. It fit a wide variety of bottles and was hollow except for the tip. We simply cut the tip off to allow the liquor to flow. To handle the breathing tube we used a t-junction and electrical-taped an &ldquo;overflow&rdquo; tube. You can see how this works in the video.</p>

<p>The OTTO team is stoked on this success and are hard at work on delivering refrigerated mixers. Please continue staying tuned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Story So Far]]></title>
    <link href="http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/the-story-so-far/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-13T11:58:43-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://OTTO-Mixr.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/the-story-so-far</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We started out having no idea how we could make OTTO a reality. Well, to go back a bit further, we started out having no idea what project we were actually competent enough to complete. An acoustic keyboard sniffer? Too much math. A differential power analysis attack? Too much what the fuck is this. An automated pancake flipper? Too many carbs. OTTO came to fruition because it was the perfect mix of engaging to work on, exciting to demo, and a good excuse to get trashed before 5. <!--more--></p>

<p>Now that we had the idea we began the hard work of making it happen. The project has two basic components: get the glass to move and find a way to dispense the liquid. As it turns out, dispensing the liquid is pretty goddamn tricky. You can pump the liquid upwards. There are definitely solutions available but they’re either expensive, ugly, slow, or some combination thereof. We saw an existing project that used breast pumps. As tempting as it is, we didn’t see ourselves marching down to Breast-Pumps-R-Us and buying 6 breast pumps. Another project used peristaltic pumps each individually controlled by an arduino connected to a raspberry pi over ethernet. That seemed way too complicated to us. Really, why not let gravity do the work? This is in fact such a good idea that another bar robot uses it. However, the makers of said robot refuse to release any schematics, part list, source code, or anything that might interfere with this idea that they seem to have that they will become billionaires from bar machines. So we had to do it ourselves.</p>

<p>The first gravity solution that we looked into was a servo that would turn a valve. After spending half an hour in Home Depot turning valves and attempting to assess the amount of torque required we learned a few things. One, there is a surprising variety of valves out there. Two, the sheer amount of torque required would necessitate an impractically expensive servo. Three, none of us fit in at a hardware store.</p>

<p>We pressed on in searching for valves for our project. Eventually, we came upon the aptly titled valves4projects. We found food safe solenoids for $14/piece <a href="http://www.ebay.com/itm/1-2-Gravity-Feed-Electric-Solenoid-Valve-DDB-CD-12VDC-/300653378588?pt=LH_DefaultDomain_0&amp;hash=item4600567c1c">here</a>! These were perfect for our project so we ordered 6. Conveniently enough, valves4projects is located in downtown San Diego. So after heading downtown for a quick pick-up, we went over to San Diego Electronic Supply where Manny the manager hooked it fat. For starters, this store is amazing as long as you can manage not to trip on the pile of boxes that greet you in the entrance, to the right of the entrance, to the right of the right of the entrance, to the left of the right of the right of the entrance, and really just the whole store. We walked in knowing basically nothing about transistors, resistors, diodes, and circuits, but, as I said before, Manny hooked it up. After giving us a brief 101 on circuits, he did some sort of wizard math and scooped up all the parts for us. We walked out of there with:</p>

<ul>
<li>6 1N4004 diodes</li>
<li>6 3.3k resistors</li>
<li>6 TIP111 transistors</li>
<li>12V 5.5A power supply</li>
</ul>


<p>for the princely sum of $14.</p>

<p>Now, the exciting part begins. We returned with our spoils and started plugging away at breadboarding it. We managed to get the solenoid opening and closing that same night. Considering that we were expecting that part to take a week or two, we were pleasantly surprised. Encouraged by this success, we began plotting our next improvement to OTTO: refrigerated mixers! Once we actually figure out how to do this, we’ll share it with you guys. Stay tuned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
